welcome to meditating with john vervicky
we live weekday morning at 9 30 a.m
eastern time we alternate typically on
mondays
uh between the dharma day in which you
teach a new lesson and then a
pie a day and then the empire days
alternate between
review of the whole ecology practices
from the eastern tradition
or reviewing the ecology of practice
from the western tradition the wisdom of
asia course
that we're on right now but right now
we're in a bit of a
an acceleration on the dharma
today is also a dharma day monday
wednesday and friday it's been a darn
day
just to announce it next monday is also
going to be a dharma day
next monday is also going to be a dharma
day
so if you're joining us for the first
time don't be put off by all of this
there's been lots of instruction in
seated practice
meditating contemplating there's been
standing practices moving mindfulness
practices etc
you're welcome to keep meeting with us
and i encourage you to do so
but i strongly recommend you go to the
description of this video you'll find
links to previous lessons do lesson one
right away
try and do you know one or two lessons a
week keep meeting with us and eventually
it'll all integrate and you'll be
integrated into the course
and hopefully into the sega community
you could all help me to help as many as
people as possible by liking this video
stream
uh decrease increase its visibility on
the youtube
search algorithm um at the end of every
session
there are q and a's there's a q a period
please limit the questions to the
ecology of practice uh we give priority
on monday wednesday and friday to
questions from
the western tradition and tuesday and
thursday
to the eastern tradition i hope you all
met on the discord
yesterday i couldn't be here yesterday
if you are interested in more general
questions um
they're every third friday of the month
at 3 pm eastern time
we live stream a general q a
so um it's important
um to also in addition to questions
to share observations comments
edification
because it's not just the buddha it's
not just the dharma
it's also the sauna all right so let's
pick up on what we're doing here we're
uh
on what's called the first degree of
wisdom the primary school
it's not sufficient but it's needed of
epicureanism with the course of wisdom
of hypatia
and we've learned some principles and
some practices
um what's the first practice we learned
we learned the practice of prioritizing
pleasure
and how to do that and then we learned
the practice of
savoring and we learned the
metallic and the peritolic sense of
adoraxia
and now we have been moving into the
disciplining
the discerning and disciplining of
imagination so whenever moments of
imagination occur to us
especially those that terrorize us and
that can lead us into
despair um we have what's called the
four-fold cure
and we we've gone through the full for
the four fold
cure on how to address that
and where that ended uh on wednesday
was that we need a practice uh
by which we can
encourage each other
and of course i'm separating that to the
sense of it's enacted
it's embodied we're right we're
training courage in each other and we're
also inspiring each other
so the full gamut both the more ancient
sense and then all the modern
meanings that attaches to that attack to
this word
and at that at the core of this and the
thing that was most valued
by the epicureans uh was friendship
um now i think friendship is an
important word and but
we have tended to lose the sense of
friendship as
a virtue and so um i'm going to bring
back
an a slightly archaic word that isn't
used as much
to try and emphasize i don't mean
friendship in just the sense we mean
today
i'm not saying you treat your friends
lightly i'm not saying that
i am not saying that what i'm saying is
we need a deeper sense of what the
epicureans were talking about when they
talk about friendship
so the word that's very helpful here i
think is fellowship
this is a word for use uh so
in fellowship uh there is friendship
but there is a friendship in the sense
of
like a community and a community that is
centered upon something centered upon
something that transcends the
individuals that make it
so uh you know christians often use this
word for that there should be fellowship
in a congregation and i think that's a
little bit closer to
the epicurean meaning of friendship
all right so we want to learn how to
cultivate a fellowship
of encouragement now this takes us into
some very important work um and today
we're going to be this is why i need to
have another dharma day on monday
today we're going to be talking sort of
more about the theory once we get a
proper framing of it i'm doing it right
now and then monday is going to be
you know the actual specific exercises
and practices
so the person whose work i'm making use
of here is the really important and
recent work
um let's hold this up for you
so this is a book
by rand lahav called the handbook of
philosophical companionships
principles procedures and exercises
that's the
sort of main book for the practice uh
has some of the theory in here
here's the book that has a bit more of a
theory behind it it's called
philosophical contemplation technique
theory and techniques for the
contemplator and that's around the half
again and then the most important book
um well not the most important sorry
the most comprehensive i use the wrong
word i apologize the most comprehensive
book
in terms of its sort of the
philosophical foundation is
stepping out of plato's cave
philosophical counseling philosophical
practice and self-transformation by ran
okay so obviously and
you know i'm not expecting all of you
guys to read all these books
i'm making it available to you so you
can use it as needed
right but my job is to
learn this material um test it out put
it into
conversation with the best sort of
cognitive science that i have learned
and then transmit uh to it to you
hopefully as helpfully as i can all
right
so what the hat has this model of what
he calls
uh philosophical
contemplative
and companionship
he sometimes shortens it to
philosophical companionships but he
wants us to always remember it has these
three components in it
so let's talk briefly about this notion
of philosophical let's draw it out
okay so courage because we're talking
about
a fellowship for encouragement because
this is the
most powerful way in which we can
respond
to fear right so
courage is a virtue you have to think
about
what a virtue is um we use this word
when we talk about
virtual like virtual reality and what we
mean
is a shaping of possibilities so that we
have practice for what is
actually um a shaping of possibilities
like when you're in virtual space it's
not real space
but it's it's shaping in you know a
possible space
a possible world hopefully to help train
you for the real world now of course
like everything else we can use it an
escapist fashion
but that's the original meaning of
virtue virtue is a power it is a
shaped potentiality to act rightly
in the world okay so
so so what well
the person who really unpacked this is
of course
aristotle and the notion of a virtue is
a wise habit
you inhabit something so you practice
until it is second nature if you think a
virtue is about
this is one of my problems with a lot of
our political discourse left and right
i'm not taking aside here
is that we have relegated unite the
ideas of virtue to the possession of
beliefs right
and that's not where aristotle for
example classically located virtue
virtue is located in a wise habit
so you have to track you have to
practice something and you know habit
can be a skill it can be a sensitivity
it could be a transformation of your
sensibility
but you practice something until it
becomes second nature
so that you inhabit it you wear it like
the habit
of a monk that the monk wears to change
their identity okay okay
so we're directed towards
a training when we're talking about a
virtue so we'll come back
to that but what about the other side
the wisdom so
for aristotle there's two aspects to
wisdom
importantly sophia and francis both of
these words are translated
both of these greek words are translated
as wisdom the fact that we have one word
for it
really hamstrings our understanding just
like we have one word for love and the
greeks have
agape and eros and philia let's fight
philia there
right sophia we'll come back to that
okay so what is this this is basically
your ability to grasp to see to have
insight
into the principles right that are
regulating the patterns of things
right so what's what's the principle
that's at work uh so you're in a
situation
and what's the principle what's the most
relevant principle at work here
that's sophia it's having an insight
into what's the relevant principle here
pronesis is yours right your sense of
what's unfolding in the process and how
can i
intervene how can i fit myself to it and
intervene
in it effectively and so what you want
to do
is you want to bring these two together
um and
for those of you who've watched some of
my other work i think i've talked about
it a bit in this
in the sangha too this is the notion of
getting an optimal
grip on things um
getting an optimal grip on the situation
so optimal grip comes from perception
right so what right perception isn't
some static thing you do
uh we've talked about this in savoring i
i i write
this is too close i'm getting details
but i can't see the gestalt
this is you know i can see the gestalt
but i'm not getting
you know all of the features and what i
want to do is get
i want to find a spot and i want to move
the thing
so i get the best overall trade-off
between
the whole the right the most
encompassing gestalt
and the specific unfolding of the
features
so i'm trying to get this these two to
come together and you're
you're probably saying and you would be
correct this reminds me it reminds me
what you talked about in the eightfold
path like the right-handedness of things
like right understanding yeah it's
exactly that idea
so right that right that so my hand
right it makes use of various principles
right in process
in order to come to an optimal grip on
it
so one way you can think about this then
is that what you're trying to do in
wisdom right is you're trying
and this is one of the overall so when
we've done a lot of work on this and
there's a consensus around this
right is that the wisdom at least
involves seeing through illusion
right in order
to get an optimal grip on a situation
so your sense of if you can grasp
the relevant principles right the more
general the more powerful patterns
and then see how they apply here and
then that's the sofia
and the and then seeing how they apply
is the phromesis
then i get i can see through illusion so
i can come into optimal grip a right
relationship
in the sense of right-handedness uh with
the situation
okay so what does that mean
well what would that mean for courage
courage would mean that you have
practiced until it is habit your
right not your belief about
principles but your ability to see them
to realize them that's what all that
maximization
is doing when right in in the epicurean
practices
we create these mnemonic packages that
help us
keep practicing seeing the principles
in action and these widen our frame
sophia so i've done that and i come into
a situation
and fear is starting to distort like in
my imagination
but then the maxims remind me of
important principles they
maximize my frame i open up to sophia
but now we're going to talk more about
yet but how do i then bring this
into process how do i bring this into
the specific situation how do i
contextualize it
and that's exactly what the virtue is
you can think about
every virtue as the way of how you're
wise in this particular situation so
to be kind is the way to be wise in this
situation
to be honest is the way to be wise in
this situation
to be courageous is the way to be wise
in this situation
that's the tight interconnection virtue
is very much
the beauty of wisdom where beauty
is how you are able to realize principle
in
process such that it fits you well
to the situation that's what beautiful
music does you
get the big pattern but how it's
impregnating
the unfolding process and it fits you
to the unfolding of the music you're
gripped by the music and you're
optimally gripping it
you're in that right relationship okay
so virtue is the beauty of wisdom
so that's what we're talking about here
we're talking about
this enacted sense making
notice the musical metaphors because
they're going to be very very
pertinent so here's the idea
when we're doing this making sense of
things
take seriously this and take seriously
the metaphor here this is both
our understanding right like the sense
of a sentence
but it's also sight and hearing
it's that connectedness to the world
making sense of things
making sense of others
and making sense with others
i have arguments for all of these and i
can't do them because i don't have time
but the point is these are all
mutually interdependent when we're
trying to make sense of things
we're almost always having to make sense
of others you also you say sometimes i'm
alone
yes but you're carrying other people's
perspectives around with you when you're
trying to make sense even when you're
alone
and making sense is ultimately something
we do together let me just give you a
non-controversial example i didn't make
any of these words
i didn't come up with them neither did
you we make
english together and we keep making it
together that's not the only way
we make sense it's just a pertinent
example here
this is where we're starting to get the
idea of why we need
philosophical contemplative
companionship
contemplation is the making sense of
things
right the the the companionship
is both making sense of others
while making sense with others
philosophical
companionship is about trying to
grasp the principles of this triangle
and then enact it
in a regular practice process okay
so let's unpack this term philosophical
contemplative companionship i already
mentioned
right philia sophia that's in the word
philosophy so i'm not talking here about
academic philosophy
academic philosophy is not right
something you should despise
um i'm always suspicious of people who
do so uh
but that's what we're talking about here
we're talking about this
this is the fellowship love of wisdom
now this word is
often used to mean actually both sophia
and phronesis together
okay so it's the foolish it's the
fellowship love
of wisdom and of course as i tried to
show you wisdom and virtue are
inherently bound up together
virtue is the beauty of wisdom
it's what makes us love wisdom
okay so look what about this word
companionship well it comes from two
latin words
companis this means with
and this means bread
and you're going what yeah this means
sharing bread with people having a meal
with people
so the basic idea here is communing
together think about when you
when you eat with other and so how much
we want to eat with other human beings
and how much rituals involve eating
with other human beings sharing bread
together
now what's going on there because the
point here is
this is not just about communication
this is about communing
so one of the things we have to get
right from the beginning about
philosophical contemplative
companionships
right is that this is not just about
communication
this is about communing it's about
communion
not just communication it's about
feeding each other
not just giving each other feedback
and there's a big difference between
those there's a very big difference
between them
so when we eat together
right notice what we're doing it and
it's we're we're sort of
enacting us we're literally mattering
we're taking in matter that makes us
and we're doing it with the people that
matter to us
and we're so we're trying to get all of
that in sync
resonating together we're eating a meal
together
and notice we use consumption like we
have to
digest an idea
okay
all right so this is telling us oh
okay so yeah i get that i get that's
that triangle
you know the making sense of things
making sense of others making sense with
others
okay sophia is both you know the prince
getting prince
right practicing principle into process
right i'm going to be communing with
other people to do that
not just communicating with them feeding
them
and being fed by them not just giving
feedback
okay
so what about this word contemplation
well we've talked about it before
remember
it mean it has to do with you know the
original meaning it has to do with the
temple
it means right divination
right in the sense of right
you know of course and that's
degenerated into people believing they
can foretell the future and stuff like
that
but originally it meant looking for
signs of the god's presence
right looking for signs of the god's
presence
and if we go back to the greek word that
contemplation is based on fioria
we get a word theory from that which is
fine but that's only half of it
right what's the original meaning of
theoria well the original meaning of
theoria is to go on a journey
so that i will see something marvelous
that will transform me
so what i'm doing is i'm trying to give
i'm leaving the familiar and
right the ordinary the normal think
about
philosophic think about contemplative
sorry think about
meditative questing gotta get the right
objective they're crucial here
right i go on a journey i leave the
familiar and the normal to see
something marvelous that will transform
me i want to be present
for a revelation i want to see something
that i haven't seen before
so this is very much a vision quest
like how it's used sometimes uh to
discuss certain practices
uh from indigenous communities you're
going on an adventure to see the advent
of something
you're trying to pick up on the
significance of things that's what the
word
significant means how it's a sign for
the presence
of something that has not been present
to you before
okay so we're trying to get away from
our normal
and familiar way of thinking
what is the normal and familiar way of
thinking well
it's the having of beliefs it's the
communicating
and not communing because what i want to
do is defend my beliefs
or give you my beliefs or perhaps
consume some useful beliefs from you
that's not communion that's not this
so i want you to pick up on all of these
metaphors
when we're doing philosophical
contemplative companionship
what we're basically doing is we're
doing something like a ritual meal
in order to see
and make present makes grasp the
significance of something
by making it present to it not just
representing it look at this word
that means it's no longer present but
actually
sensing its presence
okay so what's the meal in philosophical
companionship what's the meal we're
sharing
well the meal is actually a
it's a
short philosophical text
now it's philosophical and there's i'll
give you two
on monday i'll give you uh the website
link that we'll have
these are text where for philosophy in
the sense of philia sofia
not academic technical philosophy
but these are philosophical texts that
are designed
to be nourishing
and what we can do is we're trying to
partake in them
together we're trying to participate
in them together we're trying to take
part in them together
okay that's what we're doing at the meal
so again think about
ritual meals family meals you know
christmas time
thanksgiving what you're gathering
people together why you want to be
present with them
you want to nourish each other you right
you want to get into right relationship
with each other
so really try and uh make use of that
metaphor
okay so what are we doing how how are we
speaking well we'll get into the
specific
how on monday but again what's the
theoretical
framework we're cooperatively
cooperatively
we're cooperative together we are trying
to give voice to the text
we're trying to make that person that
author
present to us like seeing the gods
we're trying to invoke them and partake
in their presence
the idea being that when we can come
before when we can
share in the presence of that person
together
right we will and that's the amazing
thing about text it can actually do that
for us
we will be enriched in the sense of
being
encouraged encouraged
so we want to give voice to that
and here's where you're probably
thinking but you know i'm going to say
one thing and bob's going to say another
and susan's going to say another
and that's exactly right but the the
metaphor that the
have uses is we're
forming a chorus
we're singing we're trying to sing
i'm using that metaphorically the
significance of the text
so your your the point here is not
to agree or disagree with the text
the point is to bear witness to it to
try and give voice to it
to try and present make present the
spirit of augustine or the spirit of
marcus aurelius
it's like seeing the gods
you're trying to pick up on the
significance of a shared
presence rather than convince others
of your particular belief or opinion
you're trying to get away from familiar
opinion that we all have that there's
nothing wrong with it we need it in the
social context but we have that very
familiar normal way of communicating
with each other
we're trying to leave that behind in
peoria and come into communing with each
other
okay so what does that mean
well we're trying to do these three
things let's bring that triangle back
we're trying to in a coordinated and
cooperative fashion
make sense of the text not agree
or disagree or offer your opinions
the point is what is it saying to us
and not because i want to consume the
content
what i want to do is like get a family
meal i want i'm we're trying to invite
and invoke augustine or plato
or socrates or epicurus to dinner
to be here with us
and of course that means we're also
making
sense of others because i have to
appreciate think of music appreciation
we're all
we're in a chorus together i have to
appreciate i have to understand and
value what you're saying
i don't have to agree with it but that
is not relevant in this context
because we are making sense together we
are
sensing
together the meaning of the text and we
are sensing the presence
of the voice of the text
okay so what does that mean we're doing
well here's
where your previous practices are a
scaffold
for this
here's the text and it's like a meal and
what are we doing
we are co-savoring it together
we are trying to open it up like when
you're walking and you're trying to open
up
and we're trying to realize as many
patterns in it as it can as we can
not because we're trying to finish it or
come to a final belief we're trying to
listen to the musicality
of its intelligibility we're trying to
pick up
and listen together and sing together
that musicality we're co-savoring
that's why you've been practicing savory
we're learning how to co-savor the text
together
and that's not independent it's meshed
up with
savoring each other's presence together
so we're gonna pick up and partake in
right pattern the patterning of the
ideas of the text we're going to try and
pick up on
the texture right the right the tempo of
the text the tone
um the taste of it and you know we talk
about having a taste of music you're
trying to cultivate your
a taste for the text you the the
tone-ups the tensions that are in the
text like there's
tension in music you're doing all of
this because
you're trying to sense
the significance see understanding
is different from belief say
significance
understanding is about grasping the
and you should do that learn how to do
that very very deeply
before we move to any kind of critical
response to the text
so we're giving voice to the text
bearing witness to the presence
wow that's getting really sloppy
and so what we're trying what what we're
getting to
finally is this and that's where we'll
all end for today
i know it's a bit of a cliffhanger i
apologize but you know there's
limitations of time that i really have
to respect here
okay depth
you're going to be speaking from the
deepest
parts of yourself depth resonating to
depth
you are trying to move to a place you're
traveling far
from your normal everyday belief making
opinion giving self and you're trying to
go into what is emerging from you
in the depths that's almost like an
insight
like or an emotional a response
something that's on the edge of your
understanding not something that you i
get it
yes yes no but more like something what
is emerging from you
so what you're trying to do right
is get speaking from the depth from what
is emerging
and what you're what's that is doing
is you're being called by
the depth of others called to the depths
of others
and called by and called to the depth of
the text
right what's the emerging
significance here
the emerging sensing of the emerging
significance
it's a very different way
of speaking with others it's a
very different way and if we carry
our everyday listen to the word i'm
going to use habits into this practice
of how we talk with each others how we
merely communicate
state opinions consume beliefs give
feedback
we will not get any of this we will not
be engaging
in the practice of philosophical
contemplative companionship we will not
be generating a fellowship of
encouragement we need all those other
forms of communication
and we need scientific discourse and we
we need political
dispute et cetera i'm not denying that
but we also need this you know when you
need to learn how to swim
it right you have to stop trying to walk
because if you keep trying to walk in
the water you won't swim is walking
should be walking be thrown away no you
need it but you have to stop walking
in order to swim in order to learn how
to swim
okay so that's a lot and i hope it
wasn't
too overwhelming and we're going to have
a short sit now
jason's going to slightly adjust the
camera and then we'll have a short set
and then we will go into a short q a as
i keep reminding you
uh monday wednesdays and fridays are
longer there's a lot more to go
so this was the theory very abstract and
many of your things is also abstract
i sort of get it but i don't know how to
do it i get that too
monday is following up on the hive how
do we put all of that
into practice how do we bring the
principles
into practice how do we bring the sophia
of today
into the phromesis so that we can
actually start practicing it
together virtually hopefully on a
regular place
on the discord server okay so let's
everybody get into position
please get you're comfortable
please set your phones and do not
disturb
again this is a little bit strange but i
hope that's okay
this gives me i uh again because of the
meniere's i need some back support
and it also gives me access to the tv so
we'll do a quick chat and then we'll
silence it together we will begin
together when i say the word
begin
[Music]
one
on
[Music]
one
on
begin your silence set
you
[Music]
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character and community
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
so uh looks like we're pretty much out
of time for today i'm
sorry about that um hopefully we will
get more time on monday for some
questions
um please understand that uh
i anticipate that um
the schedule is probably going to change
to some degree in september so i'm
trying to get us
get us some good momentum and the wisdom
of hypatia so that we'll be able to
carry forward
through that transitional period i want
to thank everybody for joining today i
want to thank my
beloved son jason who has been making
everything happen
for us today please subscribe to the
channel to be notified of the next video
also follow me on twitter to if you feel
that's okay
uh in order to have any updates about
these streams
invite others who might benefit by
sharing this series
please join the discord server there to
discuss with others hopefully start
practicing we'll talk
i'm going to talk with mark and brad
again hopefully about the philosophical
contemplated companionship practice the
movement practices
etc reminder uh that we do this
every weekday morning at 9 30 eastern
time
final reminder that continuity of
practice is more important than
your quantity of practice don't hold
yourself to the standard of harsh
perfectionism but virtuous friendship
but think about how that's starting to
resonate even more
with us because there is no enemy worse
than your own mind and body
no friend no ally no true companion on
the path
better than your own mind and body be
lamps unto yourselves
and to each other take good care
everyone i'll see you on monday
for another dharma day